and we will now move to yes to.
Liselotte
I'm so sorry.
But we will move
to the next presentation.
Yeah. Perfect.
All right.
I'm assuming everybody can hear me
and see me.
If not, give me a shot.
So my name is Liselotte de Beer.
I'm a research fellow
at the University of Stavanger in Norway,
and the paper I'm presenting
today is entitled Post-Human Ethics
and Networked Agency
and AI Human Collaborations.
So as AI is embedded in daily life,
authorship, agency
and responsibility are harder to locate
within a singular human subject.
So this paper argues that Illit
potentially offers a useful guide here
for understanding AI human co-creation,
because it already distributes
agency across author readers,
system text, interface design, and so on.
And in doing so, the research positions
AI human co-creation
in a post-human ethics framework
that allows responsibility to be conceived
as relational and shared.
This approach may also complement
emerging AI ethics guidelines,
which includes the Unesco recommendations
on Transparency and accountability.
So the idea to be really
that it becomes practical
and something that we can
in fact use within policy discussions.
So what then of literature new text.
So new tech first of all authorship
really has debates about it
have been around for decades.
We've got author death
of the author of the codes or the function
kind of saying that singular human author
should not be the only one
responsible for a texts.
Meaning and advancements
and reliance on technology
have really just sharpened
these issues sharp in these debates.
And what I found amazing
is that with every new writing
technology, as scans points out,
we kind of just get new ways
of creating new forms of literature,
new ways of storytelling.
For instance, Illit already
kind of destabilizes
the singular authorship through mediums
that include hypertext, interactive
fiction, kind of leveraging technology
to our advantage.
And in that way, the digital space,
especially within Illit, becomes
really, really important.
The computer, the tablets,
it becomes central to the experience.
For example, Montfort's Turaco Gorge
demonstrates that authorship in Illit
is already in many ways distributed.
The author designs the rules,
and the computer system produces
multiple texts using those rules.
But already we have the digital
becoming a part of the creation process.
And for me, this really highlights
how Illit could serve
as a guide for AI human collaborations.
We're creative agency is distributed
between human and non-human actors,
and the other centrality
of the digital environment already
anticipates the way that AI can shape
not only outputs,
but the creation process as a whole.
And for me, this highlights
the importance of exploring why post-human
ethics matters, because issues on
how human responsibility changes
when creation is no longer
exclusively human becomes important.
So we're
kind of had the rules a little bit
more visible through hyperlinks and so on.
AI really obscures them quite often,
and I think that's
what makes issues on transparency
even more urgent.
Which brings me to the idea
of post-human ethics.
So in order to be able to understand
both human post-human ethics,
I think it's good to stop for a moment
and pause on what the post-human is,
which is something
almost impossible to discuss in a book,
let alone a ten minute presentation.
So I'm going to just try
and be very quick about it.
But at the core, post humanism really
questions what it means to be human.
And I want to refer to the work of Hayles,
who for me is
one of the fundamental scholars,
and her thinking is just broadened up
my mind so much.
And for her,
she really insists that the question
is not becoming post-human
because we're kind of already there.
It's a process
that's been unfolding for decades.
The question really is what kind of
post-human will be, will we be?
And for me,
this has direct ethical implications.
And here I want to highlight
the idea of posthuman subjectivity
that can provide this basis
for an alternative view of the ethics
that gets into play when there's an
increased interconnection with technology.
Because posthuman subjectivity provides
for a sense of self
that really becomes entangled
within technology.
So an ellipse, post-human subjectivity
kind of becomes
enacted for me through the interactivity,
through the network reading.
And then these human machine
collaborations and Hayles
concept of techno genesis really
further suggests that the human bodies
and the techniques behind it all, like,
kind of just shape each other.
And in that way
Eliot
reflects and enacts distributed
cognition, networked agency,
and these fluid boundaries that become
come into play when it we're working
between human and non-human actors.
And for me, this is central.
When we see that
AI and human collaborations
become more dialogic and interactive.
I think that is what paves the way
for the necessity
of considering post-human ethics,
because post-human ethics
treats agency and responsibility
as emerging
through these networks of humans
and machines,
the contrast shifts from traditional views
of who takes responsibility,
or this idea that a singular human
takes responsibility, and instead
we have responsibility
that emerges across assemblages.
And according to McCormack, post-human
ethics shifts away from more fixed systems
and instead considers
a more dynamic way of interconnection
and how humans can operate in a freer
relationship with machines that disrupt
more traditional views of power dynamics.
And what for me is really important
is that the Unesco guidelines
are quite clear
that AI systems cannot fully replace
human responsibility.
But I think that just further strengthens
the argument for saints of distributed
and then relational accountability
and agency.
So then what is distributed agency
in all of this.
So the distributed cognition of the
posthuman complicates individual agency.
This is significant
when it comes to discussions
on AI co-creation, especially
with the underlying ethical concerns.
Because ethics here becomes Nate work
and not solely in the hands of the humans
in many ways.
So Bruno Leto's conception of agency
is especially illuminating
because it views agency
as a network of influences where both
humans and non-humans interact and thereby
shape each other's actions and outcomes.
And it emphasizes
the relational nature of agency.
And this raises the potential
for seeing machine agency
at some point in the future.
I'm not at all
implying that AI has agency at present.
Just to clarify that.
And yeah, I want to use the example
of Java as rewrites, because I think it's
a perfect example of combining machine
generated text with human editorial work.
And in a way, for me, shows
distributed agency in practice.
The human editor still shapes the story,
and AI contributes unexpected
forms, unexpected rhymes,
and it shows that AI outputs are not yet
obviously self-sufficient.
But that meaning and responsibility
then emerged through human intervention
and that dialogic relationship
I was speaking about before.
The questions really sharpened,
though, around ethical responsibility.
So when we're considering
whether human and non-human actors
are ethically responsible
and how this can be determined,
if control is situated
both with human and machine
that comes becomes quite problematic.
And I think something that is worth
discussion.
Hales argues
that the assumption that humans,
and not technology,
must be in control at all times
assumes that conscious agency
is the hallmark of being human.
When we look at the post-human worldview,
actually conscious agency
has never been in control.
And rather than insisting
that control remain purely in human hands,
a post-human perspective encourages
us to rethink of agency
as distributed across this network.
So AI can be designed to reduce harm.
But the ethical outcomes
depend on a broader
assemblage that includes design
choices, training data, user prompt,
platform governance and,
I think, just society at large.
So this can become clear
when we consider interactive AI platforms.
So an example I've used here
is AI dungeon, which is an interactive
storytelling platform which combines
human input and prompt design with gen
AI in order to produce a narrative.
The platform allows the player
to choose a character, type
A various actions during the gameplay
with the AI human system, with the AI
system, and then the human player
is given the opportunity to set the scene
and determine the prompts that enable
the AI system to create the narrative.
So important here, accountability
cannot be reduced to a single entity.
Post-Human ethics
that is relational is what I'm arguing.
Steps in the focus must be on
how the assemblage is designed
and how it is used,
and how it is disclosed.
So AI and human, AI versus human.
That for me is the massive question.
And I know one
that I think has not been answered
and will not be answered for
for a while to come.
But I think distributed agency
really becomes visible within AI human
co-creation, where meaning emerges
through iterative interactions.
The human cannot be removed
from accountability,
but neither can the machine.
And perhaps then full acknowledgment
and transparency
is the necessary step forward.
And I note again,
like Unesco has proposed these,
but I think there's a far way before
we actually see
this happening in practice.
So in systems where there is co-creation
between human and AI,
the role of AI goes from a lone decision
maker to a more complex
one that's dependent on partnership.
And it is this complex
interaction and partnership
that really makes it difficult to answer
who owns the product, and who is the one
in charge of this human AI co-creation.
And this remains quite difficult
legally and ethically, and continues
to receive attention
and research and updated guidance.
Here I want to mention the Authors
Alliance.
They recently updated their guidelines
when it comes to considerations
for authors when it comes to using gen
AI and collaborations
between humans and machines is key
is a key challenge of the digital age.
And we don't.
If we don't have these guidelines, then
the ethical principles won't be there.
And these ethical principles could.
The lack of these ethical principles,
rather could really undermine
the relationships between humans and AI.
So I argue that continued guidance
guidance is really necessary. And
if we try
and step away from a singular view towards
the post-human view,
that is maybe a way that the relational
element will find its power,
and that the relational element
of the ethics can come to fruition.
It's from a posthuman perspective.
It's easier
to conceive of AI as a partner,
not simply as a tool, and especially in
the context of techno genesis
and the symbiotic nature
of technology and humanity.
And then fundamental to the ethical use of
AI is
we can mention, as outlined
by the Unesco recommendations, is that AI
systems should ideally ensure fairness
and nondiscrimination, ensure
responsibility and accountability, and
ensure transparency and explainability.
The notion of AI and collaboration.
Co-creation really also emphasizes
the importance of cost vision, but also
in order to achieve certain objectives.
And it's been argued that content
that's AI generated or where AI's
played a significant role really
should be acknowledged specifically.
And this transparency, similar to work
that's been created by like a ghostwriter,
really helps preserve trust and similar
within the reader as well as the consumer
when it comes to the content
that's been created.
Here, we can give examples of notes
of disclosure
on digital poems that clearly indicate
which parts have been used,
use machines to create,
and to what extent, because transparency
and disclosure doesn't solve the issue
of shared responsibility, but it does
make it visible and it makes it discussing
which is which is crucial.
So for me, very briefly,
just some of the implications I foresee
of conceiving of authorship
and agency has distributed is by.
Is by the fact that it changes
the way that texts are seen.
It changes
also the way the texts are understood
and analyzed and text
on not produced by a singular human,
and therefore it's produced by a singular,
by a network of relations.
And I think that's
kind of always been the case
that networks have been responsible.
Even if one person writes a whole book,
their whole network of their past
and present
and their relationships play part.
But here
I think the stakes are very different.
And now if we're talking about text
being produced by humans
and non-humans, it will include
a massive amount of stakeholders.
Developers, interface designers, even
social norms are all included within this.
And therefore interpretation cannot
only be connected to a single stable text
because viewing authorship is relational
and networked really changes
notions of ownership and copyrights.
And I think this is really important
for me, where the humanities
and the legal kind of need to try
and if they can work together
a bit on this one, it's
something that I'm really excited about
and passionate about
and think is is quite due.
Because if we think about ownership
and copyrights, not the same thing.
For example, you may own your AI
dungeon story, but copyright jurisdiction
is not the same across the world
and therefore some jurisdictions won't.
Copyright AI works,
and that makes it really, really difficult
and blurs the boundaries quite a bit.
And then finally, also distributed
authorship complicates issues of who
takes responsibility and who takes blame
or who then gets credit.
If harmful content is created
on a platform such as AI dungeon,
where does this responsibility end
and where does it begin?
And I think the first step for me
is like highlighting, obviously,
that this is a problem,
that we should be talking about it
and not just brushing AI away
as if it's something that we can just
easily erase, if you will.
So in conclusion, this
discussion really showed us
that AI necessitates
a reconsideration of the traditional views
of of ethics, and it challenges
traditional humanist assumptions
when it comes to authorship and agency.
And this is because
the more traditional views
of singular responsibility
and accountability falls short.
It doesn't account
for the interwoven and hybrid
nature of the human machine relationship
that underlies working with AI,
in whichever form and to whichever extent.
And furthermore, eyelids example
show us that creation and authorship
does not have to be
have long been seen as collaborative,
but it doesn't have to make it scary.
Then, in a sense, AI has just become
a new collaborative partner in that space.
The question then, for me
seems to be not just whether AI can create
art and literature,
which is one that a lot of people discuss
and have very strong views of, of course.
But perhaps we need to be
having conversations about how how
we share and disclose responsibility
and how we have that
help shape future literary spaces.
And here post-human
ethical lens does not dissolve human
responsibility completely, but
it makes the network of relations visible.
And this opens up more honest,
more transparent,
more accountable
forms of AI, human co-creation.
Thank you.